Finding Aid for Society of Women Engineers, University of Michigan section records, 1971-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Society of Women Engineers, University of Michigan section records 1971-2011
Society of Women Engineers. University of Michigan section
4.0 linear feet and 5 outsize volumes
9746 Bimu 2
University of Michigan section of national organization established to further interests of women engineering students. History and background information, annual reports, newsletters and newspaper clippings, budget information, photographs and scrapbooks, correspondence, and files relating to section activities
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were received from the student section (donor no. 8492 ) in 1996, 2011 and 2012.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open for research without restriction
The Society of Women Engineers (SWE) was founded in 1949 by a small group of women from the eastern United States, principally, New York, Boston, Philadelphia, and Washington, D.C. Today, the organization is national in scope with 70% of its total membership comprised of students from different university chapters. The University of Michigan student section was chartered on February 25, 1961, as a nonprofit educational organization whose purpose was to further the interests of women engineering students, and to promote in them a high standard of professional ethics.
The mission of the University of Michigan section of the Society of Women Engineers is to encourage women to excel as engineers and leaders, and to promote an inclusive community within the College and the profession that fosters universal success in engineering, independent of gender.
See the organizations website: http://swe.engin.umich.edu/ for current information.
The records of the University of Michigan student section of the Society of Women Engineers cover the period from 1971 to 2011 and have been divided into three series: Society Records, Student Activities, and Audio-Visual.
Subjects:
Society of Women Engineers. University of Michigan Section.; Engineers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women engineers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.
- Society Records
  The Society Records series (0.5 linear feet, 1971-2011) consists of historical background files, annual reports, newsletters, correspondence and budget material. The awards and recognitions file hold certificates honoring the SWE. The history file provides an overview of the organization. The annual reports are arranged chronologically and cover all activities of the student section. Though dated 1971 to 1991, there are gaps in the annual reports between 1977 and 1981. The news file includes newsletters, alumni news, and newspaper clippings. The budget file covers only academic year 1983/84, but does include the organization's treasurer's report for 1982. The student enrollment file includes records for 1973-1976 and for 1982. The correspondence file consists of a scattering of letters relating to section affairs.
  - Awards and Acknowledgements (Box 1)
  - Historical/Background Information (include handbooks and manuals) (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports, 1972-1984, 9 folders (Box 1)
  - News File (Box 1)
  - Newsletters, 1971-1991, 1996, 2010-2011, 17 folders (Box 1)
  - Alumni News, 1988-1989 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 1)
  - Budget File (includes ledger, 1983/84 and treasurer's report, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Enrollment of women, 1973-1976 (with graduation statistics for 1982) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence file, 1975-1985 (scattered) (Box 1)
- Student Activities
  The Student Activities series (0.5 linear feet, 1971-2011) consists of reports of competitions in which students participated. Based upon these reports, students received various regional and national awards. The correspondence file consists of a scattering of letters relating to section affairs.
  - Competition reports (Box 1)
  - Outreach programs for high school students (Box 1)
  - Student resumes, 1981-1990 (1983 missing), 5 volumes (Box 1)
  - SWE Region H Conference, 2011 (Box 1)
  - Activities, 2010-2011 (Box 1)
- Audio-Visual
  - Photographs (Box 2)
    - Photo Album, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
    - Photo Album, 1991 (Box 2)
    - Photo Album, 1995 (Box 2)
    - Photo Album, 1999 (Box 2)
    - Photo Album, 2002 (Box 2)
    - Photo Album, Summer Engineering Exploration, 2000 (Box 3)
    - Photo Album, date unknown (2 albums) (Box 3)
    - Photos, Summer Engineering Exploration, 2003 (3 envelopes) (Box 3)
    - Photographic prints, date unknown (Box 3)
  - CD-R
    - Summer Engineering Exploration photographs, 2003 (Box 3)
  - Videotapes
    - Summer Engineering Exploration, 2000 (Box 3)
      (VHS)
  - Negatives
    - Negative Strips, 1989-1994 (Box 3)
    - SWE Outreach slide negatives, 1987, 1989-1990, 1992 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbooks
    - Scrapbook, 1974-1975 (oversize volume 1) (Box 4)
    - National Convention Scrapbook, 1989 (Box 4)
    - Society of Women Engineers and Student Conference Scrapbook, 1990 (oversize volume 2) (Box 4)
    - Scrapbook, 1993-1994 (Box 4)
    - Scrapbook, 2000-2002 (Box 4)
    - Scrapbook, 2003 (Box 4)
    - Scrapbook, 2004 (Box 4)
    - Scrapbook, 2005 (oversize volume 3) (Box 4)
    - Scrapbook, 2006 (oversize volume 4) (Box 4)
    - Scrapbook, 2010-2011 (oversize volume 5) (Box 4)